What I'm going to do is, I'm going to explain to you
ما أنا بصدد القيام به هو أن سأفسر لكم
an extreme green concept
مفهوم أخضر أقصى
that was developed at NASA's Glenn Research Center
والذي تم تطويره في مركزأبحاث غلين التابع لوكالة ناسا
in Cleveland, Ohio.
في كليفلاند، بأوهايو.
But before I do that, we have to go over
ولكن قبل أن أقوم بذلك، يجب أن نخوض في
the definition of what green is,
تعريف ماهية الأخضر،
'cause a lot of us have a different definition of it.
لأن الكثير منّا لديه تعريف مختلف له.
Green. The product is created through
الأخضر. هو ما يتم إنتاجه عن طريق
environmentally and socially conscious means.
وسائل ذات إدراك للبعد البيئي والإجتماعي.
There's plenty of things that are being called green now.
هنالك الكثير من الأشياء تسمى الآن خضراء.
What does it actually mean?
فما الذي تعنيه على وجه التحديد؟
We use three metrics to determine green.
نستخدم ثلاثة مقاييس لتحديد الأخضر.
The first metric is: Is it sustainable?
المقياس الأول: هل هو مُستدام؟
Which means, are you preserving what you are doing for future use
بمعنى، هل ما تقوم به سوف يدوم للمستقبل؟
or for future generations?
أو للأجيال القادمة؟
Is it alternative? Is it different than what is being used today,
هل هو بديل؟ هل يختلف عن ما هو مستخدم حاليًا؟
or does it have a lower carbon footprint
أو هل به أثر كربون أقل
than what's used conventionally?
من المستخدم تقليديًا؟
And three: Is it renewable?
وثالثًا: هل هو متجدد؟
Does it come from Earth's natural replenishing resources,
هل يأتي من المصادر الطبيعية المتجددة على كوكب الارض.
such as sun, wind and water?
مثل الشمس، والرياح، والماء؟
Now, my task at NASA is to develop
حسنًا، مُهمتي في وكالة ناسا هي تطوير
the next generation of aviation fuels.
الجيل الجديد من وقود الطائرات.
Extreme green. Why aviation?
الأخضر الأقصى. لماذا مجال الطيران؟
The field of aviation uses more fuel than just about
مجال الطيران يستهلك وقوداً أكثر تقريبًا من
every other combined. We need to find an alternative.
كل المجالات الأخرى مجتمعة. نحن بحاجة لإيجاد بديل.
Also it's a national aeronautics directive.
أيضًا هو اتجاه وطني في علم الطيران.
One of the national aeronautics goals is to develop
واحد من أهداف علم الطيران الوطنية هو تطوير
the next generation of fuels, biofuels,
الجيل القادم من الوقود، الوقود الحيوي،
using domestic and safe, friendly resources.
باستخدام مصادر صديقة للبيئة ومحلية وآمنة.
Now, combating that challenge
الآن، لمواجهة هذا التحدي
we have to also meet the big three metric —
علينا أيضًا أن نحقق المقايس الثلاثة الكبرى
Actually, extreme green for us is all three together;
في الواقع، الأخضر الأقصى بالنسبة لنا هو الثلاثة مجتمعين،
that's why you see the plus there. I was told to say that.
لذلك نرى علامة الزائد هناك. طلب مني أن أقول ذلك.
So it has to be the big three at GRC. That's another metric.
لذلك يجب أن تكون هناك الثلاثة الكبار في مركزأبحاث جلين. ذلك مقياس آخر.
Ninety-seven percent of the world's water is saltwater.
97% من الماء في العالم مالحة.
How about we use that? Combine that with number three.
كيف لنا أن نستخدمها؟ اربط ذلك بالرقم ثلاثة.
Do not use arable land.
لا تستخدم الأرض الصالحة للزراعة.
Because crops are already growing on that land
لأن المحاصيل تنمو بالفعل في تلك الأرض
that's very scarce around the world.
وهي نادرة جدًا حول العالم.
Number two: Don't compete with food crops.
رقم اثنين: لا تنافس المحاصيل الزراعية.
That's already a well established entity, they don't need another entry.
إنها كيان راسخ مسبقاً، وليس هناك من حاجة لمدخل آخر.
And lastly the most precious resource we have on this Earth
وأخيرًا أكثر المصادر النفيسة التي نمتلكها على هذه الأرض
is fresh water. Don't use fresh water.
هي الماء العذب. لا تستخدم الماء النقي.
If 97.5 percent of the world's water is saltwater,
إن كان 97.5% من الماء في العالم مالحاً،
2.5 percent is fresh water. Less than a half percent
فإن %2.5 هو ماء عذب، أقل من 0.5%
of that is accessible for human use.
منه متاح للاستخدام البشري.
But 60 percent of the population lives within that one percent.
لكن 60% من الكثافة السكانية تعيش ضمن حدود ال 1% تلك.
So, combating my problem was, now I have to be extreme green
لذلك، كان التحدي هو، الآن لابد أن أتحول إلى الأخضر الأقصى
and meet the big three. Ladies and gentlemen,
و تحقيق الثلاثة الكبار. سيداتي و سادتي،
welcome to the GreenLab Research Facility.
مرحبا بكم في مرفق أبحاث المعمل الأخضر.
This is a facility dedicated to the next generation
هذا المرفق مهدى للجيل القادم
of aviation fuels using halophytes.
لوقود الطائرات الذي يستخدم النباتات الملحية.
A halophyte is a salt-tolerating plant.
النباتات الملحية هي نباتات مقاومة لملوحة التربة.
Most plants don't like salt, but halophytes tolerate salt.
معظم النباتات لا تحب الملح، و لكن هذا النوع يتحمل الملوحة.
We also are using weeds
نستخدم أيضا الأعشاب
and we are also using algae.
و كذلك الطحالب.
The good thing about our lab is, we've had
الشيئ الجيد حول معملنا هو أننا استقبلنا
3,600 visitors in the last two years.
3600 زائرا خلال السنتين الماضيتين.
Why do you think that's so?
لماذا تظنون أن ذلك قد حدث؟
Because we are on to something special.
السبب هو أننا نعمل على شيء خاص.
So, in the lower you see the GreenLab obviously,
في الأسفل ترون المعمل الأخضر بشكل واضح،
and on the right hand side you'll see algae.
و على الجانب الأيمن سترون الطحالب.
If you are into the business of the next generation
إن كنتم تريدون ولوج أعمال الجيل القادم
of aviation fuels, algae is a viable option,
من وقود الطائرات، فإن الطحالب هي خيار قابل للتطبيق،
there's a lot of funding right now,
يتوفرالكثير من الدعم حاليا،
and we have an algae to fuels program.
و لدينا الطحالب للدفع بالبرنامج.
There's two types of algae growing.
يوجد نوعان من زراعة الطحالب.
One is a closed photobioreactor that you see here,
أحدهما هو المفاعل الحيوي المغلق الذي ترونه هنا،
and what you see on the other side is our species —
و ما ترونه على الجانب الآخر هي الأنواع خاصتنا
we are currently using a species called Scenedesmus dimorphus.
نستخدم حاليا نوعا يدعى سيندسمس ديمورفس.
Our job at NASA is to take the experimental and computational
عملنا في ناسا هو إجراء الأعمال التجريبية و الحاسوبية
and make a better mixing for the closed photobioreactors.
و القيام بدمج أفضل للمفاعلات المغلقة.
Now the problems with closed photobioreactors are:
المشاكل الحالية بالنسبة للمفاعلات المغلقة هي:
They are quite expensive, they are automated,
أنها غالية جدا، و آلية،
and it's very difficult to get them in large scale.
و من الصعب جدا الحصول عليها على نطاق واسع.
So on large scale what do they use?
إذا ماذا يستخدمون على النطاق الواسع؟
We use open pond systems. Now, around the world
نستخدم أنظمة البرك المفتوحة. الآن، حول العالم
they are growing algae, with this racetrack design
يزرعون الطحالب، باستخدام تصميم مضمار السباق هذا
that you see here. Looks like an oval with
و الذي ترونه هنا. يبدو بيضاوي الشكل
a paddle wheel and mixes really well,
مع بدّالات و هو يخلط بشكل جيد،
but when it gets around the last turn, which I call turn four — it's stagnant.
و لكن حالما تصل إلى اللفة الأخيرة، و التي أدعوها اللفة الرابعة، إنها راكدة.
We actually have a solution for that.
في الواقع لدينا حل لذلك.
In the GreenLab in our open pond system
في المعمل الأخضر في نظام البركة المفتوحة
we use something that happens in nature: waves.
نستخدم شيئا يحدث في الطبيعة: الأمواج.
We actually use wave technology on our open pond systems.
في الواقع نستخدم تفنية الأمواج في نظام البركة المفتوحة خاصتنا.
We have 95 percent mixing and our lipid content is higher
لدينا 95% من الخليط و المحتوى الدهني يكون أعلى
than a closed photobioreactor system,
من نظام المفاعل الحيوي المغلق
which we think is significant.
و الذي نعتقد أنه مهم جدا.
There is a drawback to algae, however: It's very expensive.
هناك عقبة تواجه استخدام الطحالب، و هي أنها غالية جدا.
Is there a way to produce algae inexpensively?
هل من طريقة لإنتاج الطحالب بشكل أقل كلفة؟
And the answer is: yes.
و الإجابة هي نعم.
We do the same thing we do with halophytes,
نفعل نفس الشيء الذي نفعله مع النباتات الملحية،
and that is: climatic adaptation.
ألا و هو التكيف المناخي.
In our GreenLab we have six primary ecosystems
لدينا ستة نظم بيئية أساسية في معملنا الأخضر
that range from freshwater all the way to saltwater.
و التي تتدرج من الماء العذب و حتى الماء المالح.
What we do: We take a potential species, we start at freshwater,
ما نفعله هو أننا نأخذ عينات محتملة و من ثم نبدء من الماء العذب،
we add a little bit more salt, when the second tank here
نضيف القليل من الملح، و حينها يصبح الخزان الثاني هنا
will be the same ecosystem as Brazil —
مثل النظام البيئي الموجود في البرازيل
right next to the sugar cane fields you can have our plants —
بجانب حقول قصب السكر يمكنك الحصول على نباتاتنا
the next tank represents Africa, the next tank represents Arizona,
الخزان التالي يمثل إفريقيا و الخزان الذي يليه يمثل أريزونا،
the next tank represents Florida,
و التالي يمثل فلوريدا،
and the next tank represents California or the open ocean.
و التالي يمثل كاليفورنيا أو المحيط المفتوح.
What we are trying to do is to come up with a single species
ما نحاول فعله هو الإتيان بنوع وحيد
that can survive anywhere in the world, where there's barren desert.
بإمكانه البقاء في أي مكان في العالم، حيث توجد صحراء قاحلة.
We are being very successful so far.
نعتبر أنفسنا ناجحين جدا حتى الآن.
Now, here's one of the problems.
الآن، هذه واحدة من المشاكل.
If you are a farmer, you need five things to be successful: You need seeds,
إذا ما كنت مزارعا فأنت بحاجة إلى خمسة أشياء لتكون ناجحاً: فأنت تحتاج إلى البذور،
you need soil, you need water and you need sun,
و تحتاج إلى التربة، و تحتاج إلى الماء و تحتاج إلى الشمس،
and the last thing that you need is fertilizer.
و آخر شيئ تحتاجه هو الأسمدة.
Most people use chemical fertilizers. But guess what?
معظم الناس يستخدمون الأسمدة الكيميائية. و لكن خمن ماذا؟
We do not use chemical fertilizer.
نحن لا نستخدم الأسمدة الكيميائية.
Wait a second! I just saw lots of greenery in your GreenLab. You have to use fertilizer.
إنتظروا! رأيت للتو الكثير من الخضرة في معملكم الأخضر. لابد أنكم تستخدمون الأسمدة.
80 percent of what we need are in these tanks themselves.
80% من ما نحتاجه متوفر في هذه الخزانات نفسها.
The 20 percent that's missing is nitrogen and phosphorous.
ال20% المتبقية هي عبارة عن نتروجين و فسفور.
We have a natural solution: fish.
لدينا حل طبيعي و هو السمك.
No we don't cut up the fish and put them in there.
نحن لا نقطّع السمك و نحفظه هناك.
Fish waste is what we use. As a matter of fact
مخلفات السمك هي ما نحتاج إليه، في واقع الأمر
we use freshwater mollies, that we've used our climatic adaptation technique
نحن نستخدم سمك المولي، حيث استخدمنا تقنية التكيف المناخي الخاصة بنا
from freshwater all the way to seawater.
ابتداءاً من الماء العذب و حتى ماء البحر.
Freshwater mollies: cheap, they love to make babies,
يعتبر سمك المولي رخيصاً و كثير التوالد،
and they love to go to the bathroom.
كذلك يحب التردد على دورة المياه.
And the more they go to the bathroom, the more fertilizer we get,
و كلما زاد عدد مرات تردده على الحمام زاد ما نحصل عليه من أسمدة،
It should be noted that we use sand as our soil,
الجدير بالملاحظة أننا نستخدم الرمل كتربة،
regular beach sand. Fossilized coral.
رمل الشواطئ المعتاد. المرجانية المتحجرة
So a lot of people ask me, "How did you get started?"
يسألني العديد من الناس، "كيف كانت بدايتك؟"
Well, we got started in what we call the indoor biofuels lab.
حسنا، بدأنا في ما نسميه مختبر الوقود الحيوي الداخلي.
It's a seedling lab. We have 26 different species of halophytes,
إنه مختبر شتلات. لدينا 26 نوع مختلف من النباتات الملحية.
and five are winners. What we do here is —
و خمسة منها هي التي نعتمد عليها. ما نفعله هنا هو
actually it should be called a death lab, 'cause we try to
في الواقع لابد من تسميته مختبر الموت، لأننا نحاول
kill the seedlings, make them rough —
أن نقتل الشتلات، و جعلها تفسد
and then we come to the GreenLab.
ثم نأتي بها إلى المعمل الأخضر.
What you see in the lower corner
ماترونه في الزاوية السفلى
is a wastewater treatment plant experiment
هي تجربة محطة معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي
that we are growing, a macro-algae that I'll talk about in a minute.
حيث نعمل على زراعة طحالب مصغرة و التي سأتحدث عنها خلال دقيقة.
And lastly, it's me actually working in the lab to prove to you I do work,
و أخيرا، هذا أنا داخل المعمل كإثبات أني أشارك في العمل،
I don't just talk about what I do.
فأنا لا أتحدث فقط عن ما أفعل.
Here's the plant species. Salicornia virginica.
هذه هي أنواع النباتات. أشنان
It's a wonderful plant. I love that plant.
إنها نبتة رائعة. أحب هذه النبتة.
Everywhere we go we see it. It's all over the place, from Maine
أينما ذهبنا نجدها. إنها في كل مكان، من ماين
all the way to California. We love that plant.
و على طول الطريق إلى كاليفورنيا. نحن نحب هذه النبتة
Second is Salicornia bigelovii. Very difficult to get around the world.
التالية هي أشنان بيجلوفي. يصعب جدا الحصول عليها.
It is the highest lipid content that we have,
تمثل أعلى محتوى دهني يمكن أن نحصل عليه،
but it has a shortcoming: It's short.
و لكن بها عيباً و هو أنها قصيرة.
Now you take europaea, which is the largest or the tallest plant that we have.
الآن ترون اوروبي ، و التي تعتبر أكبر أو أطول نبات نعرفه.
And what we are trying to do
و ما نحاول فعله
with natural selection or adaptive biology — combine all three
عن طريق الإنتقاء الطبيعي و علم الأحياء التكيًّفي، هو دمج الثلاثة معا
to make a high-growth, high-lipid plant.
لخلق نبات ذو نمو مضطرد و محتوي دهني عالي.
Next, when a hurricane decimated the Delaware Bay — soybean fields gone —
عندما حطم إعصار خليج ديلوير-دمرت حقول فول الصويا-
we came up with an idea: Can you have a plant
أتينا بفكرة: هل بإمكاننا الحصول على نبات
that has a land reclamation positive in Delaware? And the answer is yes.
ذو خاصية إستصلاح أراضي إيجابية في ديلوير؟ و الإجابة هي نعم.
It's called seashore mallow. Kosteletzkya virginica —
إنها تدعى خبازيات شاطئ البحر. ملوخية شاطئ البحر
say that five times fast if you can.
قولوها خمس مرات بسرعة إن استطعتم.
This is a 100 percent usable plant. The seeds: biofuels. The rest: cattle feed.
هذا نبات مستخدم و بنسبة 100%. البذور: وقود حيوي. المتبقي: غذاء لقطعان الماشية
It's there for 10 years; it's working very well.
إنه موجود منذ 10 سنين، و هذا يعمل بشكل جيد جدا.
Now we get to Chaetomorpha.
الآن نأتي إلى Chaetomorpha.
This is a macro-algae that loves
هذه طحالب كبرى و التي تحب
excess nutrients. If you are in the aquarium industry
المغذيات الزائدة. إن كنتم على علاقة بصناعة المصائد البحرية
you know we use it to clean up dirty tanks.
فستعرفون أننا نستخدمها لنتظيف الخزانات المتسخة.
This species is so significant to us.
تعتبر هذه الأنواع ذات أهمية بالنسبة لنا.
The properties are very close to plastic.
خصائصها شبيهة جدا بالبلاستيك.
We are trying right now to convert this macro-algae into a bioplastic.
حيث نحاول حاليا تحويل هذه الطحالب الكبرى إلى بلاستيك حيوي.
If we are successful, we will revolutionize the plastics industry.
إن قدر لنا النجاح، فسنحدث ثورة في صناعة البلاستيك.
So, we have a seed to fuel program.
لذا لدينا بذرة لبرنامج الوقود.
We have to do something with this biomass that we have.
لابد أن نفعل شيئا حيال الكتلة الحيوية التي نملكها.
And so we do G.C. extraction, lipid optimization, so on and so forth,
لذلك نقوم باستخلاص جي سي و تحسين المحتوى الدهني ذهابا و إيابا،
because our goal really is to come up with
لأن هدفنا الفعلي هو الإتيان
the next generation of aviation fuels, aviation specifics, so on and so forth.
بالجيل الجديد من وقود الطائرات، تفاصيل الطيران، و هكذا دواليك.
So far we talked about water and fuel,
حتى الآن تحدثنا عن الماء و الوقود،
but along the way we found out something interesting about Salicornia:
و على طول الطريق اكتشفنا شيئا مثيرا للإهتمام يتعلق بالأشنان:
It's a food product.
أنها مُنتَجْ غذائي
So we talk about ideas worth spreading, right?
نحن نتحدث عن أفكار تستحق الإنتشار، أليس كذلك؟
How about this: In sub-Saharan Africa, next to the sea, saltwater,
مارأيكم بهذا: في الصحراء الكبرى بأفريقيا، و بجانب البحر، الماء المالح،
barren desert, how about we take that plant,
و في الصحراء القاحلة، ماذا لو أخذنا تلك النبتة،
plant it, half use for food, half use for fuel.
ثم زرعناها، نستخدم نصفها للغذاء، و النصف الآخر للوقود.
We can make that happen, inexpensively.
نستطيع تحقيق ذلك، و بشكل رخيص.
You can see there's a greenhouse in Germany
توجد بيوت دفيئة في ألمانيا
that sells it as a health food product.
تبيعها كمنتجات غذائية صحية.
This is harvested, and in the middle here is a shrimp dish, and it's being pickled.
هذه تم حصادها، و في المنتصف هنا طبق روبيان وقد تم تخليلها.
So I have to tell you a joke. Salicornia is known as sea beans,
سأخبركم بدعابة. الأشنان معروفة بفول البحر،
saltwater asparagus and pickle weed.
نبات الهليون و مخلل الأعشاب.
So we are pickling pickle weed in the middle.
لذلك فنحن نخلل مخلل الأعشاب في المنتصف.
Oh, I thought it was funny. (Laughter)
أوه، اعتقدت أن ذلك مضحك. (ضحك)
And at the bottom is seaman's mustard. It does make sense,
و في القاع يوجد خردل البحَّار. هذا يعني شيئا،
this is a logical snack. You have mustard,
هذه وجبة خفيفة منطقية . أنت تمتلك الخردل،
you are a seaman, you see the halophyte, you mix it together,
إذا أنت بحَّار، تأخذ النباتات الملحية و تخلطها ببعضها البعض،
it's a great snack with some crackers.
انها وجبة رائعة مع بعض المكسرات.
And last, garlic with Salicornia, which is what I like.
و أخيرا، الثوم مع الأشنان و هو ما أحب.
So, water, fuel and food.
اذا، الماء و الوقود و الغذاء.
None of this is possible without the GreenLab team.
لاشيء من هذه محتمل من دون فريق المعمل الأخضر.
Just like the Miami Heat has the big three, we have the big three at NASA GRC.
كما أن فريق كرة السلة حرارة ميامي لديهم الثلاثة الكبار نحن أيضا كذلك في وكالة ناسا
That's myself, professor Bob Hendricks, our fearless leader, and Dr. Arnon Chait.
و هم أنا و بروفيسور بوب هيندركس و قائدنا الشجاع و دكتورأرنون شايت.
The backbone of the GreenLab is students.
أما العمود الفقري للمعمل الأخضر فهم الطلاب.
Over the last two years we've had 35 different students
خلال السنتين الماضتين كان لدينا 35 طالبا مختلفا
from around the world working at GreenLab.
من حول العالم يعملون في المعمل الأخضر.
As a matter fact my division chief says a lot, "You have a green university."
في الحقيقة فقد قال رئيس قسمي الكثير، "لديك جامعة خضراء."
I say, "I'm okay with that, 'cause we are nurturing
فقلت، "ذلك شيء جيد بالنسبة لي، لأننا نربي
the next generation of extreme green thinkers, which is significant."
الجيل القادم من المفكرين الخضر و هو شيء مهم جدا."
So, in first summary I presented to you what we think
لذلك، في الملخص الأول قدمت لكم ما نعتقد
is a global solution for food, fuel and water.
أنه حل عالمي للغذاء، و الوقود، و الماء.
There's something missing to be complete.
و هناك شيء ناقص حتى تكتمل الصورة.
Clearly we use electricity. We have a solution for you —
من الواضح أننا نستخدم الكهرباء. لدينا الحل بالنسبة لكم
We're using clean energy sources here.
نحن نستخدم مصادر طاقة نظيفة هنا.
So, we have two wind turbines connected to the GreenLab,
لدينا اثنين من توربينات الرياح موصلة مع المعمل الأخضر،
we have four or five more hopefully coming soon.
و لدينا أربعة أو خمسة أخرى متوقعة قريبا.
We are also using something that is quite interesting —
أيضا نستخدم شيئا مثيرا للإهتمام جدا
there is a solar array field at NASA's Glenn Research Center,
لدينا ألواح طاقة شمسية في مركز أبحاث غلين التابع لوكالة الفضاء الأمريكية ناسا،
hasn't been used for 15 years.
لم تستخدم منذ 15 سنة.
Along with some of my electrical engineering colleagues,
برفقة بعض من زملائي المهندسين الكهربائيين،
we realized that they are still viable,
أدركنا أنها مازالت قابلة للحياة،
so we are refurbishing them right now.
لذا فنحن نعمل على تجديدها في الوقت الحاضر.
In about 30 days or so they'll be connected to the GreenLab.
في خلال 30 يوما أو نحو ذلك سيكونون على اتصال بالمعمل الأخضر.
And the reason why you see red, red and yellow, is
و السبب في أنكم ترون أحمر، و أحمر، و أصفر هو
a lot of people think NASA employees don't work on Saturday —
أن الكثير من الناس يعتقدون أن العاملين في ناسا لايعملون في يوم السبت
This is a picture taken on Saturday.
هذه صورة تم إلتقاطها يوم السبت.
There are no cars around, but you see my truck in yellow. I work on Saturday. (Laughter)
مامن سيارات بالجوار، و لكن ترون شاحنتي باللون الأصفر. فأنا أعمل يوم السبت (ضحك)
This is a proof to you that I'm working.
هذا بمثابة إثبات لكم أنني أعمل.
'Cause we do what it takes to get the job done, most people know that.
لأننا نفعل كل ما يتطلبه الأمرلإنجاز العمل، و الكثير من الناس يعرف ذلك.
Here's a concept with this:
هنا الغرض من من هذا الأمر:
We are using the GreenLab for a micro-grid test bed
نحن نستخدم المعمل الأخضر في اجراء اختبار السرير الشبكة الصغرى
for the smart grid concept in Ohio.
لمفهوم الشبكة الذكية في أوهايو.
We have the ability to do that, and I think it's going to work.
لدينا المقدرة على فعل ذلك، و أعتقد أن الأمر سينجح.
So, GreenLab Research Facility.
إذا، مرفق أبحاث المعمل الأخضر.
A self-sustainable renewable energy ecosystem was presented today.
نظام بيئي ذو طاقة متجددة مستدامة تم تقديمه لكم اليوم.
We really, really hope this concept catches on worldwide.
نأمل و بشدة أن يُتَبنَّى هذا المفهوم في جميع أنحاء العالم.
We think we have a solution for food, water, fuel and now energy. Complete.
نعتقد أن لدينا الحل لمشاكل الغذاء، و الماء و الوقود، و الآن الطاقة بشكل كامل.
It's extreme green, it's sustainable, alternative and renewable
إنه أخضر أقصى، إنه بديل مستدام و متجدد
and it meets the big three at GRC:
و يقابل الثلاثة الكبار في جي آر سي:
Don't use arable land, don't compete with food crops,
لا تستخدموا الأراضي الصالحة للزراعة، و لا تتنافسوا مع المحاصيل الغذائية،
and most of all, don't use fresh water.
و الأهم من ذلك، لا تستهلكوا الماء العذب.
So I get a lot of questions about, "What are you doing in that lab?"
أتلقى الكثير من الأسئلة حول، "ماذا تفعل في ذلك المعمل؟"
And I usually say, "None of your business, that's what I'm doing in the lab." (Laughter)
و عادة ما أقول، "ليس من شأنك، هذا ما أفعله في المختبر" (ضحك)
And believe it or not, my number one goal
و صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا، هدفي الأول
for working on this project is
من العمل في هذا المشروع
I want to help save the world.
هو أني أريد المساعدة في إنقاذ العالم.